<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Brent Hargrave</title>
  <id>https://brent.is/writing</id>
  <link href="https://brent.is"/>
  <link href="https://brent.is/writing/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2017-03-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Brent Hargrave</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Why do you freelance?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://brent.is/writing/why-freelance/"/>
    <id>https://brent.is/writing/why-freelance/</id>
    <published>2017-01-30T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2017-03-22T12:35:05-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Brent Hargrave</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It affords you &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Time to pursue your own mission.&lt;br&gt;
Time, and the &lt;em&gt;integrity&lt;/em&gt; to pursue that mission instead of committing years to someone else&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you freelance alone, though, you&amp;rsquo;re struggling to advance your cause. Ambitious projects grow on momentum, built atop &lt;em&gt;consistent&lt;/em&gt; effort. Yet consistency is impossible when navigating the &amp;ldquo;feast or famine&amp;rdquo; of solo freelance work. Time that opens up between engagements is wasted if you put everything on hold when the next engagement begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is simple, right? &lt;em&gt;Distribute the work&lt;/em&gt;. So you start asking your talented friends to help out. But this also fails: you don&amp;rsquo;t always know their availability, and you certainly can&amp;rsquo;t guarantee it.&lt;br&gt;
Consistency still eludes you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you could do as so many have done before: hire people to guarantee their time. But you guarantee their salaries in exchange, and full-timers expect a career path. Congrats, you&amp;rsquo;ve just started an agency!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But was that your ambition? To run an agency?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not ours. And if it&amp;rsquo;s not yours either, come work with us. We&amp;rsquo;re trying something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re a small group of creatives designing an unusual organization, one that retains the desirable aspects of the &amp;ldquo;agency model&amp;rdquo; (a respected shared brand, inspiring colleagues, a full pipeline of attractive projects) and jettisons the rest (forfeiting control over your time, work environment, and project choice to secure a salary).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our plan, in a nutshell:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborate on shared practices and tools that, over time, will stabilize our freelance work. Lean on that stability to pursue our respective goals more effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In helping one another, attract a deeper bench of like-minded colleagues to work with. As the team is excellent, so is the work: mission-focused creatives do great work because, &lt;em&gt;by definition&lt;/em&gt;, we care so deeply about results.&lt;sup id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The work attracts more, and more attractive, client engagements. Jon Lax put it best: &amp;ldquo;There is no magic to this business. If you do good work, you get good work.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all this speaks to you, &lt;a href="mailto:everyone@singularcollective.co"&gt;say hello!&lt;/a&gt; We can&amp;rsquo;t wait to discuss your ambitions, your skills and your availability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href="https://singularcollective.co"&gt;Singular Collective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us have been through startup wringer at least once. And we use the broad term &amp;ldquo;creative&amp;rdquo; deliberately: we want members with skills of &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; stripe applicable to our work.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="#fnref1" rev="footnote"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20161221104240id_/http://www.teehanlax.com/story/teehan-lax"&gt;The Making of Teehan+Lax&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="#fnref2" rev="footnote"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A reminder.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://brent.is/writing/reminder/"/>
    <id>https://brent.is/writing/reminder/</id>
    <published>2015-09-09T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2017-03-22T12:34:58-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Brent Hargrave</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had few connections in New York when I moved here six years ago. I lucked out, though, and arrived during &lt;a href="http://socialmediaweek.org"&gt;Social Media Week&lt;/a&gt;, a conference filled with tech professionals. I attended every event I could. Another entrepreneur I met that week, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/brett1211"&gt;Brett Martin&lt;/a&gt;, had also recently moved here and was equally eager to make connections. He had a vision for a mobile app we both could have used that week, one that would show you who is nearby and what interests you share with them. It promised to help me make new connections in the city, so I joined Brett to help bring it to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back on my time building that app, which we later named &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonar_%28mobile_application%29"&gt;Sonar&lt;/a&gt;, my chief regret was my failure to measure its effectiveness at its purpose: increasing the rate at which we make new connections. Of course, everyone on the team understood that was our goal. But we lacked a quantifiable, &lt;em&gt;visualizable&lt;/em&gt; measure of it. We measured and improved the metrics every startup ought to (acquisition, engagement, referral, etc.), but those metrics are popular precisely because they’re generalizable. Any product can show an increase in referrals, but the reason customers evangelize a product is unique to that product. For Sonar, I believe that would have happened once a customer noticed the app growing their social network. What if we had measured that network growth directly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, I suspect we could have. In order to surface people nearby with shared connections and interests, Sonar asked customers for access to their networks on Foursquare, Facebook, Twitter, and LinkedIn. With that data we could have plotted a customer&amp;rsquo;s total connection count over time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="connection-count-over-time" src="feed.xmlconnections-count.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to measure our impact on customers&amp;rsquo; social connections, we could have measured the change in that curve over time, their &amp;ldquo;connection rate,&amp;rdquo; before and after joining the service:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="connection-rate-change" src="feed.xmlconnect-rate.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would Sonar have evolved differently had I built that visual? Who knows… that’s unknowable. But I believe it would have buttressed us against the turmoil typical of startups, helped us stay focused, by serving as a persistent reminder of the value we hoped to deliver, the change we hoped to affect, and of how close we were to achieving that goal. As a reminder of why we chose &lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt; in the first place, over all other pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write this now, years after Sonar folded,&lt;sup id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; because I still want the product that Sonar might have been, one that helps me form relationships more frequently than I otherwise will. So I’ve begun building a new product, superficially different from Sonar, but with the same purpose. How it works is irrelevant, I’ll change it until it&amp;rsquo;s effective. But this time around, I won&amp;rsquo;t lose sight of the goal. I’ll build the reminder I need to ensure it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See Brett&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@brett1211/postmortem-of-a-venture-backed-startup-72c6f8bec7df"&gt;Postmortem of a Venture-backed Startup&lt;/a&gt; for color.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="#fnref1" rev="footnote"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
